Finding Aid for Institute of Transportation Engineers, Michigan Section Records, 1946-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Institute of Transportation Engineers, Michigan Section records 1946-2003
Institute of Transportation Engineers. Michigan Section.
7 linear feet
88430 Bn 2
Formerly the Institute of Traffic Engineers. Organizational documents, administrative files, membership materials, newsletters, correspondence, district materials, and record books of secretary and treasurer.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 4729 ) was donated to the library beginning in 1969. Periodic additions have been received.
The record group is open to research.
The Institute of Traffic Engineers (ITE) was founded in 1930. According to the constitution, its goals were "the advancement of the art and science of transportation engineering, the fostering of transportation education, the stimulation of original research in transportation engineering, the professional improvement of its members, the encouragement of intercourse between person with mutual interest in transportation engineering, and establishment of a central point of reference and union for its members." In 1976 after four years of consideration, the Institute changed its name from "Traffic" to "Transportation" engineers in order to increase the scope of its activity and to insure participation of individuals concerned in any way with the movement of goods and people. Specifically, this broadened scope of activity reflected a growing awareness of, and interest in, the variety of mass transportation methods and facilities.
Locally, the Institute functions through sections (chapters), representing individual states, regions, or nations. The Michigan Section of the ITE was unofficially organized on January 28, 1944. In March of 1946 the section was officially recognized and chartered by the international organization. The section had sixty-eight members in 1972 (the fourth largest membership behind New York, Illinois, and California).
The Michigan Section was the first to hold technical conferences (1967), and the first to establish a Technical Projects Committee. In 1981 the section had eight committees, two involving technical interest. The technical committees and conferences are among the most regularly held and attended in the section.
In addition to an annual meeting, the Michigan Section has monthly meetings held in various locations around the state. These meetings are the most popular, combining social and business activities, and providing the broadest opportunity for participation in the affairs of the Institute.
The Michigan, Indiana and Ohio sections together form District III of the Institute. The District also holds an annual meeting as well as an occasional conference. By agreement the leadership of the District passes on a rotation basis among the three sections.
The records of the Michigan Section of the Institute of Transportation Engineers date from 1946 to the present. The record group has been divided into the following series: Early organizational records, 1944-1976; Officers' Record Books; and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Engineering--United States.; Traffic engineering--United States.; Transportation--United States.
- Early organizational records 1944-1976
  The Early organizational records spans three separate time periods: 1946-1948, 1956-1964, and 1966-1978, and has been organized into six subseries: Organizational Documents, Administrative files, Membership Activities, Correspondence, District III files, and Miscellaneous. This series documents the Institute's basic concern with highway safety and related issues, specifically the question of uniform traffic signal devices, highway use taxes, safety regulations, traffic movement, and mass transportation methods and facilities. Documentation of these concerns is strongest for the years since 1966. Unfortunately, for the years before, there is sketchy information and almost nothing at all about the process by which ITE formulated its policy decisions.
  - Organizational documents 1946-1976 (Box 1)
    "Organizational Documents, 1946-1976" (1 folder) includes a representative sample of international, district, and section constitutions, bylaws, and charters. District and section lists and maps are also included. The original 1946 constitution of the Michigan Section and later revisions are among the most important items. A copy of a 1981 "officer guidelines" (manual) and charters for student chapters on the campuses of Michigan State University and the University of Michigan are also included. The documents are arranged chronologically within the three levels of organizational hierarchy, starting with the national level.
  - Administrative files 1946-1976
    "Administrative files, 1946-1976" (6 folders) includes policies, annual reports, minutes of the executive board and board of directors; secretary and treasurer reports, annual lists of officers and committee members and membership rosters. Several unincorporated association bank account papers are also included. The executive board's annual reports, the treasurer's reports and the membership and officers lists form the complete portion of other administrative files. In contrast, the executive board minutes cover only 1970 to 1973 and 1976, the board of directors minutes are for 1973 only, and the secretary's reports are very spotty after the 1950s. However, this can be partially remedied by reviewing the annual secretary's report in the Michiganite newsletter after 1966. Materials are arranged chronologically within each folder.
    - Executive board policies and annual reports 1946-1972 (Box 1)
    - Executive board minutes and board of directors minutes 1970-1976 (Box 1)
    - Secretary and treasurer reports 1946-1975 (Box 1)
    - Annual list of officers and committee members 1946-1972 (Box 1)
    - Membership rosters 1947-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Membership activities 1944-1978
    "Membership Activities, 1946-1978" (7 folders) includes minutes, reports, resolutions, project activity, schedules and notices of regular and special meetings and committees. The collection of meeting notices is only complete for the years 1946, 1947, 1958, 1971, 1972 and 1974. The minutes of monthly meetings are also incomplete; only the periods, 1946-1948 and 1957-1964 are well represented. Both groups can be supplemented by referring to the Michiganite. The Uniform Traffic Control Devices Committee folder consists of drafts and a final copy of a manual prepared between 1968 and 1971. The minutes of special meetings include the constitutional convention of 1971 and the "unofficial" organizing meeting in 1944. "Committee Reports" is the most incomplete file with only the years 1950, 1962, 1967 and 1971-1972 partially represented. Some reports are printed regularly in the Michiganite. This series also includes a folder of resolutions. The resolutions cover the period of 1944 to 1972 with the bulk spanning the years 1966 to 1969. The resolutions cover a broad range of topics, from calls for federal highway studies, prohibition of tire studs in Michigan, to the expression of sympathy to families of deceased section members. The majority of the resolutions, however, concern legislation at levels of government for traffic safety programs and regulations.
    - Minutes of monthly meetings 1946-1976 (Box 1)
    - Committee reports 1950-1972 (Box 1)
    - Uniform Traffic Control Devices Committee project 1968-1972 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of special meetings 1944-1971 (Box 1)
    - Resolutions 1944-1972 (Box 1)
    - Annual meeting schedules 1950-1974 (Box 1)
    - Monthly and annual meeting notices 1946-1974 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    "Correspondence, 1946-1976" (5 folders) includes original and copies of incoming and outgoing letters pertaining to general business. There are also letters received from the affiliated Engineering Society of Detroit.
    - General correspondence 1946-1975, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Affiliate correspondence 1964-1969 (Box 1)
  - District III
    "District III, 1959-1972" (2 folders) includes meeting minutes and notices and three copies of the district newsletter from 1959 to 1960. The minutes and notices span the years 1959 to 1972, but they are very sporadic and incomplete. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
    - Minutes and meeting notices 1959-1972 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1968-1971, undated (Box 1)
    "Miscellaneous, 1968-1971 and undated" (1 folder) includes testimony and remarks of members before Congress and the Section respectively; a manual on technical activities, a statement on the purpose of student project papers competition, and a blank ITE application form. While several items are undated, the remarks and testimony date from 1969 to 1971. The papers are arranged chronologically with undated items at the end.
- Officers' Record Books
  Officers' Record Books consists of volumes of records maintained by different ITE officers in the period of approximately 1979 to 2003. Although there are some differences in these volumes depending upon the office held, each usually contains minutes and agendas of executive board meetings, treasurer's reports, membership materials, and scattered correspondence and memoranda. This part of the record group also includes a few subject folders and audit miscellanea.
  - 1979-1982 (Secretary's record book) (Box 1)
  - 1980-1982 (Record book of secretary, later vice president, Richard F. Beaubien) (Box 1)
  - 1982-1983 (Record book of president, Richard F. Beaubien) (Box 1)
  - 1983 (Record book of secretary, Richard Cunard) (Box 1)
  - 1984-1985 (Record book of secretary, David Bacon) (Box 2)
  - 1984-1985 (Record book of director and secretary, Joseph Marson), 1 volumes (in 1 folder) (Box 2)
  - 1984-1988 (Records of officers, Donald Wiertella and Joseph Marson), 2 volumes (in 7 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1988 (Record book of vice president Joseph Marson) (Box 2)
  - 1988-1989 (Record book of vice president Roger Walther) (Box 2)
  - 1988-1989 (Record book of director Samuel Lawson) (Box 2)
  - 1988-1989 (Record book of treasurer Kenneth Tsuchiyama) (Box 2)
  - 1987 (Record book of treasurer) (Box 3)
  - 1990-1991 (Record book of secretary Joseph L. Meszaros) (Box 3)
  - 1992 (Record book of secretary David F. Allyn) (Box 3)
  - 1993 (Record book of secretary), 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - 1994 (Record book of secretary) (Box 3)
  - 1995 (Record book of treasurer) (Box 3)
  - 1996 (Record book of secretary) (Box 4)
  - 1997 (Record book of secretary) (Box 4)
  - 1997 (Record book of treasurer) (Box 4)
  - 1998 (Record book of treasurer) (Box 4)
  - 1999 (Record book of secretary) (Box 5)
  - 2000 (Record book of secretary) (Box 5)
  - 2001 (Record book of secretary) (Box 6)
  - 2002 (Record book of secretary) (Box 6)
  - 2003 (Record book of secretary) (Box 6)
  - 2000 (Record book of treasurer) (Box 7)
  - 2001 (Record book of treasurer) (Box 7)
  - 2002 (Record book of treasurer) (Box 7)
- Topical files
  - Annual meeting materials 1986-1988 (Box 5)
  - Annual reports 1982, 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - Awards and citations (Box 5)
  - Financial and audit miscellanea 1983, 1991, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Printed materials
    - Technical project reports and other printed miscellanea (Box 5)
    - Mailing circulars (Box 5)
  - Traffic and Safety Product Display Session 1978-1988, 10 folders (Box 5)